[SPEAKER_00]: And somebody is asking Venerable Sariputta, what is happiness and what is suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he replies, birth is suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: No birth is happiness.
[SPEAKER_00]: When there is birth, this is the kind of suffering you can expect.
[SPEAKER_00]: When there is no birth, you can expect this kind of happiness.
[SPEAKER_00]: No cold, heat, hunger, thirst, defecation or urination.
[SPEAKER_00]: No contact with fire, sticks or knives.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, you can expect, but there is no birth then.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is... how should then birth be understood?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you know, the life taken personally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that which is born, taken personally.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha describes birth as, you know, coming out of womb and manifestation of the aggregates into this world.
[SPEAKER_01]: But people seem to sort of misconstrue that in a sense that they think that manifestation ended once you came out of womb.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's birth and it still is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jāti.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, jāti.
[SPEAKER_01]: The manifestation that you are now is all due to you coming out of the womb.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all of this now, heat, cold, relatives, all of that is that birth.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because of that birth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the birth is not
[SPEAKER_01]: confined to, like, a little moment that lasted for, like, I don't know, half an hour on average or an hour.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Manifestation persists because of the birth and the birth is the manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for as long as you manifested, you are born.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that now, wherever you are here, you are within the country because you crossed the border, because you entered it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are manifested here now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I don't need to find out where you crossed the border, and how, and how long it lasted, or observe it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that you are inside here, inside of this country, I know that you have... you must have crossed the border.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you were born.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your manifestation is what your birth is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when... but this is some part that when one is sort of
[SPEAKER_01]: Freed from ignorance, he frees himself from birth.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't undo coming out of womb, but you can undo appropriation and ownership of that manifestation, which was your birth, which was through your birth, which was because of your birth, which is what your birth is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Practically speaking, people would, you know, wonder, because often jāta is mentioned, birth is mentioned in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, birth is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, birth is suffering, exactly, and all the suffering is
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, if birth is that physical coming out of womb, if it's confined to that only, how can you undo that?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're then subjected to all of this because... Well, first of all, you don't even have a memory of your own birth.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't seen yourself coming out of womb.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't recollect that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if that's your birth, truly, if it's only confined to that event,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's utterly inaccessible to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's something that you can understand, let alone abandon.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you take birth to be much broader phenomenon, such as, ah, this manifestation that endures here, sickness, aging, cold, elements, words of others, that is basically manifested here, aging and so on, ah, that's the birth.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's because of the birth.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what birth is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being born means being manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for as long as that manifestation endures,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can then address that directly by, yeah, uprooting the ownership of it, by seeing that everything that's within that manifestation, everything that manifests, whatever has the nature of manifestation, cannot be yours because of that, because it has arisen on its own and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are subjected to birth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Subjected to aging, subjected to death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamentally, you're subjected to that, not knowing that you're subjected to
[SPEAKER_01]: Aging, birth, elements, annoying relatives.
[SPEAKER_01]: You take the ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: You assume it's yours, you assume it's you, you assume it's for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, it's yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because of that, you suffer on account of it, and everything that pertains to that manifestation will be affecting you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, but if you...
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I say your life is enough?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, your life is the manifestation, but your life is that which is manifested in the broadest sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you then disown your life without destroying it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can see that birth as that phenomenon that you are subject to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this manifestation that you find in the world, your form, that it is you, so to speak, you had no say in it at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, all these little projects, my wishes and dreams and all my little things I'm doing, or issues, cold, heat and so on, when seen in that light of that greater context of
[SPEAKER_01]: In your form, in your birth, in your overall set of aggregates, you were subjected to it, people still assume the ownership of it and perpetuate that ownership through acting out of those, that very form, seeking pleasure in form, as the Buddha would say, as if it is theirs.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they know it's not theirs, but when the pleasure presents itself, you act as if it is yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't care, in other words.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you act out, because you can.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you're borrowing something, because it's free.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignoring the fact that, well, it's still borrowed, so sooner or later you have to pay for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why it's always compared to the Mara's trap, and similar.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you have to refrain from borrowing that which you know it's not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is not yours?
[SPEAKER_01]: Eye is not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ears, nose, mouth, body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feelings are not yours, thoughts are not yours, but you're taking them as yours because you can, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why you have to contemplate the danger to undo that attitude of, oh, I'll just take this because I'll get a quick pleasure through it, quick satisfaction, quick peace, to satisfy my desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to see the danger to prevent yourself from borrowing that which you know you shouldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: From taking the ownership of that which you know you dig down, you don't really own.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you now see that non-ownership, that context of non-ownership in regards to birth, this manifestation, you develop that perception from time to time and make it steady.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you, I mean, maybe before you do that, you would think, no, you're not going to really try to develop, do anything in your life, you know, you're not going to, because life is not mine, you know, I don't have to take responsibility, you know, I just sit down, relax and let things go.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the, of course, that's anything, even the
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't possibly address that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't possibly say, well, yeah, you know, how can we prevent that from happening?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's up to people to decide.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all of the instruction presupposes that the person who is listening to this is authentic, wants to be free from suffering, has already taken responsibility for their own situation,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't have to be, yeah, throwing things away, destroying your body,
[SPEAKER_01]: Not borrowing it does not mean destroying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yes, people will destroy it, because for as long as it's there, it's tempting me to borrow it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's the catch.
[SPEAKER_01]: To learn how not to borrow it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not to destroy it, so you're not tempted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you borrowed it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to pay for it, because you destroyed it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Plus, you're not using it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: You broke it, you bought it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You broke it, you bought it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's exactly it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how to be in the world?
[SPEAKER_01]: How to be in the world and not be with the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Precepts thoroughly taken seriously.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing the danger in the slightest fault, as the Buddha says.
[SPEAKER_01]: Guarding of the sense doors.
[SPEAKER_01]: We spoke about it often.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like I adhere to these precepts because I'm Buddhist or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: I adhere to these precepts because they're prerequisites for containing my mind that needs training.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that training starts to
[SPEAKER_01]: be put in place through sense restraint and guarding of the sense doors.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's, for example, like, when something is not against the precepts, but you still don't necessarily do it, if you know that it's rooted in desire, mentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you guard your sense doors, because that's where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, is this rooted in unwholesome desire or not?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not, is this according to the vector of the
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to take it up from that impersonal mechanical observation, observances, and make it, make it, like, take responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I keep the precepts, because I want to develop the mind, and I also guard the sense restraint, or guard the sense doors, and practice sense restraint on account of the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not an offense to, I don't know, eat between 8 and 12 in the morning, but, again, how much I eat,
[SPEAKER_01]: What I eat, why I eat, how often I eat in that period, all of that is not against the precepts, but it can very much still be the behavior that feeds your desire if you don't check that as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you guard your sense doors, and you're moderate, and you also practice sense restraint within the precepts which you already keep.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how you basically fortify yourself against the direction and the pull of the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're in the world, but not with that world, on the same level.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's the same whether you're a monk or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have to be contemplating the danger in that world, then, as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, that contemplation, I mean, will be sort of... you'll be revolving around that one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you already had enough, let's say, determination to take on the precepts and decide to practice out of them, yeah, that's already implies exactly some recognition of danger of not doing so, danger of going back to the to the previous state of non-restraint and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, that's how you will basically, as I said, fortify your mind and then all these things
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing the greater context, well, then that can actually arise, can be seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you people would not necessarily be able to see it, because the mind is still far from the necessarily developed basis for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not dry enough from sensuality, it's not withdrawn enough from company and dependence on others, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't see the
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's one thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you understand, or you can actually
[SPEAKER_00]: Be aware of the context of jhāti, of birth, being present.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is greater?
[SPEAKER_00]: What surmounts that?
[SPEAKER_00]: What context surmounts that?
[SPEAKER_00]: And I would say that is, you know, that's the context of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's implicit in the manifestation is the cessation of manifestation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no matter how
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just going to... Yeah, it's on the basis of manifestation that you have no say.
[SPEAKER_01]: That has its own direction and expiry date.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're not privy to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inaccessible to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you only see the front of it, given to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you... so, then, if you... now, you develop in the context of death, but you have to first develop the context of... Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, context of death is developed correctly,
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness of death is practiced correctly only if the extent of life is seen for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, in that sense, you... when you understand the context of death, then... then... Well, then, dispassion is the result.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like what we do next.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing sustained that, and you will...
[SPEAKER_01]: uproot any passion, desire, ill will, irritation, ownership, resistance, and so on, expectations in regard to any manifestation whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever has the nature to manifest, that's why it has a nature to cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as you're saying, so you're not going to get to be able to see that greater phenomenon of jhāti, of birth,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is going to be like an abstract view, an idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like... and sometimes people might actually, yeah, sort of get the idea, but then recognize that it's abstract, and then they think, oh, so now I need a new idea, or a better idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, now you need to elevate your mind to meet the abstracted idea, so it ceases to be abstracted from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to bring your mind to where that idea is, not change the idea to fit where your mind is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you bring it again to virtue, sense restraint, moderation, watchfulness and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: The direct training.
[SPEAKER_01]: That also implies responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot irresponsibly guard the sense doors.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot irresponsibly say no to your sensual desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: Lack of responsibility is tied with the desire, with saying yes, with the flow, going with the grain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you are practicing sensory strength and moderation and watchfulness, that implies responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reflection.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the more you develop it, the more of that reflexive recognition of that responsibility you will have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I just carelessly, irresponsibly said no to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, what am I responsible for?
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't need to be anything specific.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm responsible for accepting this manifestation of this birth, for acting out of it as if it's mine, as if it is mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I responsible for for creating birth?
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not responsible for the manifestation of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not responsible for these liabilities of cold, hunger, so on and whatever else bothering me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm not responsible for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I'm responsible if I take up the ownership
[SPEAKER_01]: of this form that's experiencing all of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how you then become invested in fearing cold, heat, elements, misfortune, craving for pleasure, craving for escape, craving for cover-ups, ill-will towards people they don't know you, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you took the ownership of the basis that's subjected to those things.